The Brain Before Birth
During the nine months when a child is developing inside its mother, the brain is very flexible and grows in an amazing fashion. By the end of the first month, the baby is producing half a million neurons (or nerve cells) every single minute! These are the tiny entities that will eventually allow the brain to do its work. Over the next few weeks, these nerve cells gather in the brain. There, they begin to reach out to each other and establish synapses---points of contact with other neurons---at a rate of two million a second. By seven months, the baby's brain has more nerve cells than it ever will again, more than it will ever be able to use, even as an adult.

