Although no one knows for sure what the future holds, researchers expect that there will be serious problems if we don't stop global warming. The sea level could rise between 18 cm (7 inches) and 58 cm (23 inches) by the end of the century. This would mean that large parts of Southeast Asia and other low-lying coastal lands would be covered with water. Increased temperatures could make it difficult for farmers to grow a sufficient amount of food, causing critical problems and possibly leading to starvation in some areas. Damage from heat waves, wildfires, and other extreme weather events would likely increase. This will cause financial loss as well as the loss of human lives. Many governments and individuals are using all the resources they can to try to save the environment and solve the problem of global warming.

