Almost Human
by Mary Roach
A      Daybreak is sudden and swift. Cued by the dawn, thirty-four chimpanzees awaken. They are still in the nests they built the previous night, in trees at the edge of an open plateau.

B      These are savanna-woodland chimps, found in eastern Senegal and across the border in western Mali. Unlike their better-known rain forest kin, savanna-woodland chimps spend most of their day on the ground. There is no tree canopy here. The trees are low and grow sparsely. It's an environment very much like the open, scratchy terrain where early humans evolved. For this reason, chimpanzee communities like the Fongoli group are uniquely valuable to scientists who study the origins of our species.

C      Life on the savanna is exceptionally harsh. If you are a primate used to greener terrain, you must adjust your behavior to survive. Our earliest hominin (meaning bipedal ape) ancestors evolved more than five million years ago during the Miocene, an epoch of extreme drying that saw the creation of vast tracts of grassland. Tropical primates no longer had plentiful fruits and year-round streams and lakes. They were forced to adapt, to range farther in their search for food and water, to take advantage of other resources. In short, to get creative.

D      In 2007 Jill Pruetz, an anthropologist at Iowa State University, reported that a Fongoli female chimp named Tumbo was sharpening a branch with her teeth and wielding it like a spear. She used it to stab at a bush baby--a pocket-size, tree-dwelling nocturnal primate. Until that report, the regular making of tools for hunting and killing mammals had been considered uniquely human behavior. Over a span of 17 days at the start of the 2006 rainy season, Pruetz saw the chimps hunt bush babies 13 times. There were 18 sightings in 2007. It would appear the chimps are getting creative.

E      Chimps that live on the ground, rather than in the safety of treetops, tend to be wary of large strangers. Jill Pruetz spent four years getting the Fongoli chimpanzees accustomed to the presence of humans--what primatologists call habituating them--and the past three summers observing them. Six days a week, from dawn to dusk, she follows the chimps.

F      It is not glamorous work. It's hot and filthy and exhausting. Home is a mud-walled hut shared with 30 Fongoli villagers. Dinner is peanut sauce over rice, except when it's peanut sauce over millet. If the chimps wander unusually far, Pruetz gets back to the village so late that her portion has long ago been fed to the dogs. Sometimes, rather than hike the five miles back to camp, she curls up and sleeps on the ground. She has gotten malaria seven times.

G      Yet you rarely meet people who love what they do as much as Pruetz does. Right now she is sitting on the ground, jotting notes with one hand and slapping sweat bees with the other. The payoffs have been dramatic. In addition to using tools to hunt, Fongoli chimps have been seen exhibiting some other novel behaviors: soaking in a water hole, passing the afternoon in caves.

H      At 24 square miles, Fongoli is the largest home range of any habituated chimpanzee group ever studied. Harvard primatologist Craig Stanford likens foraging over a large range to knowing one's way around an enormous supermarket. Like Pruetz, he believes the chimpanzees are not foraging at random, but moving with foresight and intent. "You don't stroll down the aisles hoping to catch a glimpse of the broccoli. You know where each item is, and in which months seasonal foods are likely to be in stock." The same, he thinks, holds true for chimpanzees.

I      The shift toward eating more meat may have played an important role in the evolution of a larger, more sophisticated brain. Here's how the thinking goes. To keep a bigger brain functioning, some other organ or system needed to become more streamlined. A chimp doesn't have to eat nearly as much of an energy-rich food like meat as he would of low-nutrient plant matter.

J      As if on cue, a female named Tia appears in our sight lines 20 feet ahead, sitting on a boulder pulling raw flesh off a limb like a picnicker with a comically huge drumstick. Pruetz raises her binoculars, then lowers them again. It's a bushbuck. That's the biggest animal I've seen them eat." They are the largest prey on record for a chimpanzee.

K      Adult female and juvenile chimps--the low rankers--have been seen hunting bush babies most often. This makes sense. Dominant males are not generous with food they find, and no one can force them to share. Fongoli females appear to have taken matters into their own hands.

L      Around Fongoli, the animals are accorded a remarkable amount of respect by locals. Kerri Clavette, Pruetz's student, interviewed villagers about their beliefs regarding chimpanzees and whether they hunted them. Among the region's main tribes, chimps--compared with monkeys--have an elevated, almost human status. Behaviors normally associated with a baser nature--such as walking on all fours--were given a respectful spin: "Chimpanzees walk on their knuckles to keep their hands clean to eat with."

Why do researchers think the Fongoli chimps are important to study?
