L      Around Fongoli, the animals are accorded a remarkable amount of respect by locals. Kerri Clavette, Pruetz's student, interviewed villagers about their beliefs regarding chimpanzees and whether they hunted them. Among the region's main tribes, chimps--compared with monkeys--have an elevated, almost human status. Behaviors normally associated with a baser nature--such as walking on all fours--were given a respectful spin: "Chimpanzees walk on their knuckles to keep their hands clean to eat with."

Why do researchers think the Fongoli chimps are important to study?
