Good afternoon, I’m Yoshito. Today, I would like to talk about brain wave. Most of you enter password to use your smartphone. For example, you use number, pattern, fingerprint and iris. These days, camera’s quality is getting better.  So, when fingerprints and irises are scanned once, you will have a serious problem for security. But if you use brain wave to use smartphone, you won’t have to worry about security. How is brain wave used? Why is brain wave good for security? Brain waves are detected differently for each person when you view several images. So, even if your brain wave is scanned, it’s safe for security because you only have to change the image to be displayed. In the future, brain wave might be scanned from wireless earphones. Thank you for listening. 
