"Mature" usually means "adult, physically and mentally developed" but in Paragraphs I and J, it is used in a different sense. What can you infer that a "mature field" is?
1つ選択してください:
a. a huge field recently discovered in an easily accessible location 
b. an old oil field discovered in 1900 that has been abandoned today 
c. a deposit that has been used for many years and now doesn't have as much oil 
d. a previously unknown oil deposit that computers have identified
