What is the best summary of Pruetz's research?
1つ選択してください:
a. In the savanna habitat, chimps have developed techniques that may be similar to early humans. 
b. Male chimps do not share food with females and juveniles, so they have to obtain their own food. 
c. Female chimps make tools to use against external enemies that try to take their territory. 
d. The Fongoli chimps live in a harsh environment, but they seem to have adapted well.
