Later Brain Development
During the next few years, the first areas a child's brain learns to master are sensory information and movement. After that, he or she starts to gain perspective on more abstract concepts, such as the relationships among objects in space and how to use language. The last area to develop is the executive brain, the aspect of thinking that helps us make social judgments, weigh alternatives, plan for the future and control our own behavior. This area is not fully developed until the age of 25. That may explain why some teenagers who have adult ideas, energy, and emotions sometimes get in trouble when these forces get out of control.
