Earth is showing many signs of climate change. Average temperatures around the world have climbed 0.8 degrees Celsius since 1880. The speed of warming is also increasing, with the years from 1980 to 2000 being the hottest in 400 years. The ice in the Arctic region is melting rapidly, and this area may experience its first completely ice-free summer by 2040. Further south, coral reefs, which are affected by tiny changes in water temperature, suffered the greatest losses ever recorded in 1998. In some places, as much as 70 percent of the reef area died. Scientists predict that as temperatures continue to rise in the next 50 years, these sorts of events will also increase.
