A group of more than 2,500 scientists from more than 130 countries released a report in 2007 saying that humans have caused all or most of the current warming. The growth of industrial operations, the loss of forest lands, and increased quantities of air pollution have all added to the problem. We are putting so much pollution into the environment that plants and oceans cannot handle it. Even if we can stop all the activities that cause this pollution, the problems would still continue for many years.
