
Scientists are continually discovering extraordinary information about the human brain, such as how it produces consciousness, how memories are stored and where emotions come from. New computer-based visualizing techniques have revealed a lot about these amazing accomplishments. At the same time, some researchers are focusing on changes that take place in the brain over time, beginning with the initial transformations that happen while the baby is still inside its mother, and through to childhood, adulthood, and into old age. Michael Merzenich of the University of California, San Francisco says, "Ten years ago most neuroscientists saw the brain as a kind of computer, developing fixed functions early. What we now appreciate is that the brain is continually revising itself throughout life."
