

Limestone: From Under the Sea to Sky High
Rock climber, Chris Sharma, digs his fingertips into holes on the side of a giant rock. It's limestone rock--"perfect for extreme climbing," Sharma says. The rock is full of bumps, holes, and cracks that make it easier for climbers to hold on to. However, limestone rock didn't start out this way.

400 million years ago, water covered the area where Sharma is climbing. The rock he hangs from used to be tiny pieces of sea animals. When prehistoric sea animals died, their soft parts decayed into nothing. Their hard parts, like coral skeletons and shark teeth, didn't decay. They settled on the seafloor. Year after year, more hard parts drifted down and piled up. Layers of mud and sand settled on top of it, too. The weight of all these pieces pressed down. Over time, the layers hardened into limestone.

Limestone forms on the seafloor. Yet Sharma climbs high up on cliffs. How did limestone rise so high? Over time, Earth's crust, or top layer, kept changing. In some places, the weather got colder or drier. The ocean dried up so the water disappeared. The limestone seafloor became dry land.

Giant pieces of the Earth's crust smashed into each other, too. These large pieces, called tectonic plates, move all the time. When the hit each other, they can create hills, even mountains. As a result, limestone shapes some of the world's most amazing peaks.

For Chris Sharma, he loves the feeling of rock climbing. He smiles as he imagines how, over time, water wore away at this land to create so many rocky spires. "For me, the great part about climbing is that it really connects you to the natural world," he says. Limestone rock makes up much of the Earth's crust. They tell stories of our planet's past. They build its beauty today. They will create rock-climbing challenges for many years to come.

