Good afternoon, I’m Yoshito. Today, I would like to talk about brain wave. Most of you enter password to use your smartphone. For example, you use number, pattern, fingerprint and iris. These days, camera’s quality is getting better. It is easy to scan fingerprints and irises and you will have a serious problem for security. But if you use brain wave to use smartphone, you won’t have to worry about security. How is brain wave used? Why is brain wave good for security? Brain waves are detected differently for each person when you view several images. So, even if your brain wave is scanned by other people, it’s safe for security because you only have to change the image being displayed. In the future, brain wave might be scanned from wireless earphones and brain wave
is used for security check. Thank you for listening. 
