Living in Outer Space

Airplane designer Burt Rutan is trying hard to help develop a business based on private space travel. He hopes his scheme will allow people with enough money the option of experiencing weightlessness and the thrilling views of Earth that are available from space. At the same time, a team of 16 nations is cooperating on another mission related to outer space---the construction and operation of the International Space Station (ISS), where groups of people will be able to live and work for long periods of time.

The ISS has been under construction since November 1998. In that year, Russia launched the first piece, the Zarya Control Module, into space. The station is located about 240 miles (390 kilometers) above Earth and has welcomed teams of people from many countries since November 2000. In 2008, the United States added a two-billion-dollar laboratory, increasing the structure to eight rooms.

Team members and supplies are carried back and forth by U.S. and Russian spacecraft. Space travelers, or astronauts, usually live and work there for about six months before returning to Earth. By spending time in this place, astronauts are able to learn much about what happens to humans aboard a spacecraft when they spend long periods of time in a relatively small space. The teams have learned about difficulties in a world in which food and drink don't taste the same, and where it may be hard to get a good night's sleep because it is necessary to be attached tightly to your bed.

While staying on the ISS, the astronauts are busy doing scientific experiments as well as working on the construction and improvement of the space station. In addition to these tasks, they are required to keep up a demanding program of physical exercise in order to prevent the bone loss and general weakness that can result from long periods of time in a weightless environment. The plan is for the ISS to be completed by the year 2010. By then it will be larger than a five-bedroom house.
