

The Great Barrier Reef's Food Chain
For many animals that live in the Great Barrier Reef, life follows the simple rule of eat or be eaten. As one animal eats another, energy moves from one living thing to another. This process is called a food chain.

The energy that flows through a food chain begins with the sun. Algae are plants in the sea that use the sun's energy to make food. This is a process called photosynthesis. Some algae live inside coral polyps, the animals that build coral reefs. The algae helps the polyps survive.

Coral polyps eat algae as well as small fish and shrimps. They are shaped like tubes. One end attaches itself to a hard surface. The other end has a mouth and tentacles, or arms. These arms stretch out and grab food as it passes by. This is another link in the food chain.

Polyps are a great snack for a parrotfish. The parrotfish's mouth is hard enough to break the stony outside of a polyp so that it can eat the soft parts inside. Energy moves up another link in the food chain. The polyp keeps the parrotfish alive, but not for long.

The parrotfish doesn't see a deadly predator swimming above it. With a powerful stroke of its tail, a shark dives towards to parrotfish and rips into it. The energy from the parrotfish moves into the shark and up the next link on the food chain.

Eventually, the shark dies. Its body slowly settles to the bottom of the sea. Then other links in the food chain, like crabs and certain kinds of bacteria, take over. They break down the body parts of the shark and form the final link of the chain. This food chain is an example of the movement of energy within an ecosystem.

