
Nanotechnology has been referred to as the 'science of small'. It involves the use of extremely tiny machines in fields as diverse as medicine, solar power and high-speed communications. How small are these devices? Nanotech scientists use the nanometer which is one billionth of a meter! Medical researchers are already discovering how nanotechnology can help diagnose and treat a variety of diseases. However, there are extensive possibilities for the use of this radical new technology outside the medical field.

New Solar Power Options
Solar power provides an environmentally-friendly way to use less of the earth's limited supply of carbon-based fuels such as oil. However, with traditional technology, solar collectors must be allocated a lot of space while producing only limited amounts of power. However, nanotech applications will revolutionize the field. Instead of using heavy wood, metal and glass structures, tiny solar cells will be added to a liquid plastic and applied to other surfaces, almost like paint. This will create a portable electrical supply. For example, a sweater coated in this material could power a cell phone. A car painted with the substance could potentially supply enough energy to charge the car's battery. Some researchers even believe that thin layers of plastic spread across a number of the world's deserts could generate enough clean energy to supply the power needs of the entire world.

Nanotechnology and the Internet
In recent years, the speed with which information is transmitted over the Internet has improved because of the fiber-optic cable. It allows information to be carried in the form of light which moves much faster than electrical signals do. Although the information travels quickly through the cable, it slows down a lot when it must enter a new computer network. At that point, the information must be turned back into electronic form and go through a series of time-consuming transfers before becoming a light signal again. Using nanotechnology, scientists believe they will one day be able to greatly multiply the speed of this transfer by creating a material that will allow data carried as light to pass directly from network to network with no electronic delay. Researchers say users will soon become accustomed to an Internet that is about 100 times faster than it is today.

Tiny, Tiny Tools
As the extremely small devices produced through nanotechnology become more and more common, tools to clean and service them are becoming a high priority. Even the smallest amount of dirt can render machines at the nano-scale useless. However, regular brushes made of animal hair, plastic fibers or metal fibers don't do a thorough enough job. Imagine how small the tools will have to be if the machine is smaller than the period at the end of this sentence! One of the first things researchers have created is a brush made from tiny bits of carbon. The hairs in this brush are a thousand times smaller than a human hair and yet they are strong enough to do their job with very few incidences of failure.

